<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file 
  distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership. The ASF licenses this file to you under 
  the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may 
  obtain a copy of the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to 
  in writing, software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF 
  ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language governing permissions and limitations under 
  the License. -->
<chapter
  version="5.0"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xml:lang="en">
  <title>How to begin</title>

  <section
    id="What Apache Directory Server is">
    <title>What Apache Directory Server is</title>
    <para>
      This section describes what Apache Directory Server (abbreviated ApacheDS) is, and where it comes from.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="System vision" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="Origin and Motives" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="Resources" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section
      id="System vision">
      <title>
        System vision</title>
      <para>
        ApacheDS 1.5 is an embeddable, extendable, standards compliant, modern LDAP server written entirely in Java,
        and available
        under the Apache Software License. Other network protocols like Kerberos and NTP are supported as
        well (and even
        more may be added), but basically (and especially for this introduction guide) ApacheDS is an LDAP
        server.</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Embeddable</emphasis>
        means that it is possible to configure, start and stop ApacheDS from other Java components,
        especially
        application servers, and the server runs within the same VM. The solution has already been
        successfully embedded
        in Apache Geronimo, JBoss, and others. The fact that the server is embeddable is quite
        interesting, nevertheless
        you also have the deployment option to run the server standalone, for instance as a
        Windows service. Perhaps you
        know this situation from other LDAP servers – open source (like OpenLDAP) as well
        as commercial ones (like Sun
        Java System Directory Server). This guide is dedicated to people that are new to
        ApacheDS. The guide concentrates
        on installing, configuring and running ApacheDS in a standalone configuration.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Extendable</emphasis>
        means that the modern architecture of the solution provides many extension points. Write your own
        partitions to
        store directory data, interceptors to add functionality, etc. by implementing certain interfaces
        and plugging
        them in using Spring.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Standard</emphasis>
        compliant means that ApacheDS 1.5 adheres to all RFCs relevant to
        LDAPv3. Please note that version 1.0 of the
        server has been successfully certified by the Open Group in September
        2006 ("LDAP certified"). Thus LDAP clients
        may rightly expect that ApacheDS behaves like they expect.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Modern</emphasis>
        means
        that ApacheDS aims modernize the LDAP territory, as well as it favors standards compliance. New rich
        integration
        tier constructs like LDAP Stored Procedures and Triggers are being built on top of existing
        standards.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Entirely</emphasis>
        written in Java means that the software compiles and runs on a huge number of hardware and software platforms.
        Native installers are available for Windows, MacOS and Solaris (both SPARC and intel platform), but in fact the
        set of possible targets is by far more extensive.
      </para>
      <section
        id="Architectural overview">
        <title>Architectural overview</title>
        <figure
          id="50k FT Architecture">
          <title>50k FT Architecture</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="images/50k-ft-architecture.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section
      id="Origin and Motives">
      <title>Origin and Motives</title>
      <para>
        Through his experiences with enterprise LDAP directories, Alex Karasulu, realized there is a great need
        for
        rich integration tier constructs like LDAP Stored Procedures, Triggers, and Views. In 2001 he set out to
        alter
        the OpenLDAP server to offer support for these useful facilities which are present in relational databases
        but
        missing in the LDAP world. Alex's attempts failed due to the complexity of the software which was brittle,
        and
        difficult to manage. As C code ported to several platforms, the OpenLDAP code base, had several #IFDEF
        conditional pre-compiler directives that made it difficult to change the code. At this point Alex thought about
        implementing a new LDAP server in pure Java. Thanks to NIO this was finally possible using the 1.4 JDK.
      </para>
      <para>
        In October 2002 Alex Karasulu founded and registered the
        <link
          xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ldapd">LDAPd</link>
        project at SourceForge.net. LDAPd was a a
        pure Java embeddable LDAP v3 protocol daemon built on the Avalon
        framework. Alex donated the code to the Apache
        Software Foundation and the code entered the
        <link
          xlink:href="http://incubator.apache.org/">Apache Incubator</link>
        in October 2003. One year later in October of
        2004,
        the Apache Directory Top Level Project (TLP) was formed after
        a successful incubation with the now called
        Apache
        Directory Server as its flagship product. After 4 years of
        development, in October 2006, Apache Directory
        Server
        1.0 was released as an Open Group certified LDAPv3 protocol
        server. The certification has been renewed in
        September 2007.
      </para>
      <para>Having a standards compliant and modern LDAP server, Apache Directory Team is now working on Identity and
        Access Management solutions leveraging the directory technology.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section
      id="Resources">
      <title>Resources</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link
              xlink:href="http://directory.apache.org/community%26resources/proposal-for-an-apache-directory-project.html">Proposal for an Apache Directory Project</link>
            the original proposal for incubation, September 2003.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link
              xlink:href="http://directory.apache.org/community%26resources/ldap-renaissance.html">Architecting the Modern LDAP Renaissance: The Apache Directory Vision</link>
            , Paper for 1st International Conference on LDAP, September 2007.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section
    id="Some Background. Directories, directory services and LDAP">
    <title>Some Background. Directories, directory services and LDAP</title>
    <para>This section provides a brief overview about directories, directory services and LDAP. Furthermore you find
      links to different resources (books, online resources, ...), which may act as introduction to the topic. If you
      are
      already an LDAP expert, you'll probably skip this section.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="directoriesAndDirectoryServices" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="ldapTheLightWeightDirectoryAccessProtocol" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="ldapResources" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section
      id="directoriesAndDirectoryServices">
      <title>Directories and directory services</title>
      <para>Generally speaking, a directory is a collection or list of data. Real world examples are telephone books
        (public or within organizations), church/land registers and listings of works (e.g. the Koechel-index, which
        lists
        all compositions of Mozart). All these examples have the purpose to preserve information and to make it
        available
        on demand to whom it may concern.</para>
      <para>
        Within information technology the term
        <emphasis
          role="bold">directory</emphasis>
        is used for a special kind of data storage. It allows the
        structured storage and efficient retrieval of objects
        which are often derived from the real world (e.g. persons,
        IT equipment). Characteristic:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              all data is stored in so called
              <emphasis
                role="bold">entries</emphasis>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>the set of entries within a directory forms a tree (hierarchical database)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        A
        <emphasis
          role="bold">directory service</emphasis>
        is a solution which offers users access to the information stored in the directory. A
        directory assistance (call
        center agent) is a good real world example for such a service. Within information
        technologies, such services are
        normally provided by software components. Directory services provide access to
        the content of a directory via a
        well-defined interface. If a network is used, an appropriate protocol has to be
        defined. LDAP (see below) is such
        a
        protocol.
      </para>
      <para>
        The real world examples mentioned above may be stored in such a directory, although other types of storage
        systems
        can be more appropriate (this depends on circumstance/requirements). At first sight directories compete
        thereby as
        data storage with the established relational data bases. However in the most large enterprises and
        organizations
        both directory services and relational databases are actually used. Read how Vikas Mahajan
        describes directories
        and databases as complementary, not competitive, solutions in his excellent article
        <link
          xlink:href="http://support.novell.com/techcenter/articles/ana20011101.html">"Should I Use a Directory, a Database, or Both?"</link>
        .
      </para>
    </section>
    <section
      id="ldapTheLightWeightDirectoryAccessProtocol">
      <title>LDAP – the Lightweight Directory Access Protocol</title>
      <section
        id="What is it? Some history">
        <title>What is it? Some history</title>
        <para>
          The comprehensive standard
          <emphasis
            role="bold">X.500</emphasis>
          , finalized in 1988, builds the foundation for many of today's directory
          solutions. Within this standard, the
          client accesses the server via the Directory Access Protocol (
          <emphasis
            role="bold">DAP</emphasis>
          ), which
          is OSI protocol stack based. With the Internet boom in the nineties, the accessibility of directories
          via
          TCP/IP
          became more and more important. Hence a TCP/IP-based access method, which in functionality was a
          subset
          of DAP,
          was standardized in 1993: the
          <emphasis
            role="bold">Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP)</emphasis>
          . First LDAP implementations
          were
          gateway solutions, they mediated between LDAP clients and X.500 servers. In
          1995
          the University of
          Michigan
          presented the first native LDAP server; in the meantime the work is continued by
          the
          OpenLDAP project.
          1996
          Netscape followed with the first commercial LDAP server (Netscape Directory Server,
          foundation of several
          later
          LDAP servers). Other examples (among many others) include Microsoft Active Directory
          and Novell
          eDirectory. The
          figure below shows the development of directory protocols from X.500/DAP to LDAP.
        </para>
        <figure
          id="From X500 to LDAP">
          <title>From X500 to LDAP</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="images/fromX500toLDAP.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Information model primer">
        <title>Information model primer</title>
        <para>
          Within the information model of LDAP, data is stored in entries, which build up a hierarchical, tree like
          structure. Each entry has a unique name (
          <emphasis
            role="bold">DN, Distinguished Name</emphasis>
          ), which depicts its position within the tree.
          An
          entry consists of key/value pairs, the
          <emphasis
            role="bold">attributes</emphasis>
          . Some attributes may occur more than once within an entry
          (single or multi valued, e.g. a person can have more
          than one telephone number). So called
          <emphasis
            role="bold">object classes</emphasis>
          define, which attributes an entry may have, and which of them are required. The classes build up a hierarchy
          with
          <emphasis
            role="bold">top</emphasis>
          as root; there is a parallelism to the object oriented world. top forces only the attribute
          objectclass, which
          assigns an entry its object classes. A
          <emphasis
            role="bold">schema</emphasis>
          consists object classes and attribute types,
          and therefore defines, what kind of entries can be stored within
          the
          directory. Directory servers ship a
          schema
          out-of-the-box, often with elements standardized by RFCs. In
          addition,
          most directory solutions allow
          you to
          define custom object classes and attributes. But in practice,
          the
          pre-defined
          elements are used.
          Sometimes
          they
          get extended according to special requirements.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Common applications of LDAP based directories">
        <title>Common applications of LDAP based directories</title>
        <para>LDAP operations include entry creation, modification, deletion and search. As a general rule, LDAP
          directories are optimized for read and search operations, at the cost of write performance. Data, which will
          be
          modified often, therefore better suits in a relational database, which offers better support for
          transactions and
          referential integrity as well. Directories are rather used if comparatively stable data has
          to
          be provided
          centrally. </para>
        <para>Common examples are network resources (printers, services) and user data (including credentials and rights
          for the resources). As a notable feature, many directory products offer replicas, which permit better access
          times and higher availability especially in geographically dispersed organizations. Not for nothing, the most
          common LDAP application is the enterprise phone book. That even Microsoft Outlook may be an LDAP client in
          this
          case - most average users probably don't know.</para>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Examples of software components which support LDAP">
        <title>Examples of software components which support LDAP</title>
        <figure
          id="LDAP-Tools">
          <title>LDAP-Tools</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="images/ldap-tools.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          Very different types of software products may act as LDAP clients, consuming data for authentication,
          authorization or data presentation etc.
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>E-Mail clients (e.g. Mozilla Thunderbird)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>LDAP tools (e.g. Apache Directory Studio)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Web servers (e.g. Apache Tomcat, Apache HTTP Server)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Mail servers (e.g. Apache James)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>...</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          Configuration details for several of these programs in conjunction with ApacheDS are described in later
          sections.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section
      id="ldapResources">
      <title>LDAP resources</title>
      <section
        id="Books">
        <title>Books</title>
        <para>There are several good LDAP books available. Here are two examples which provide sample chapters on their
          homepages.</para>
        <para>
          Understanding and Deploying LDAP Directory Services
          <figure
            id="Cover Understanding and Deploying LDAP Directory Services">
            <title>Cover Understanding and Deploying LDAP Directory Services</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/cover_howes_100.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          Understanding and Deploying LDAP Directory Services (2nd Edition)
          by Timothy A. Howes, Mark C. Smith, Gordon S.
          Good, Tim Howes
          Addison-Wesley Professional, 2nd Edition 2003
          ISBN: 0-672323-16-8
          <link
            xlink:href="http://awprofessional.com/title/0672323168">Book's Homepage (Howes)</link>
        </para>
        <para>
          LDAP fuer Java-Entwickler
          <figure
            id="Cover LDAP fuer Java-Entwickler">
            <title>Cover LDAP fuer Java-Entwickler</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/cover_zoerner_100.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          LDAP fuer Java-Entwickler – Einstieg und Integration.
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="images/de.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          von Stefan Zoerner
          Software und Support Verlag, 3. aktualisierte Auflage 2007
          ISBN: 978-3-939084-07-5
          <link
            xlink:href="http://www.entwickler-press.de/buecher/ldap/">Webseite zum Buch (Zoerner)</link>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Articles, forums, blogs and other online resources">
        <title>Articles, forums, blogs and other online resources</title>
        <section
          id="Blogs">
          <title>Blogs</title>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <link
                  xlink:href="http://blogs.sun.com/roller/page/DirectoryManager">cn=Directory Manager - All about Directory Server</link>
                , Sun Blog
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section
          id="Articles and other online resources">
          <title>Articles and other online resources</title>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <link
                  xlink:href="http://www.redbooks.ibm.com/abstracts/SG244986.html?Open">Understanding LDAP - Design and Implementation</link>
                , IBM RedBook, July 2006
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <link
                  xlink:href="http://www.oreillynet.com/pub/a/sysadmin/2006/07/27/demystifying-ldap.html">Demystifying LDAP</link>
                by Brian K. Jones, O'Reilly Network
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <link
                  xlink:href="http://www.mitlinx.de/ldap/">LDAP verstehen mit linx</link>
                , by Petra Haberer
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata
                      fileref="images/de.png" />
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section
    id="Installing and starting the server">
    <title>Installing and starting the server</title>
    <para>This section describes how ApacheDS can be installed and started on different platforms.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="prerequisites" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="Download a server installer" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="Installation on Windows" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="Installation on Mac OS X" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="Installation on Linux and Solaris" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section
      id="prerequisites">
      <title>Prerequisites</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis
              role="bold">Java 5.0</emphasis>
            . We recommend using
            <link
              xlink:href="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index.jsp">
              Sun's JDK</link>
            , but the server has also been successfully tested
            with JRockit 5.0 and with IBM Java 5.0.
            You can check your
            java installation with:
            <para>
              <screen>java -version</screen>
            </para>
            this should response something like:
            <para>
              <screen><![CDATA[
java version "1.5.0_06"
Java(TM) 2 Runtime Environment, Standard Edition (build 1.5.0_06-b05)
Java
HotSpot(TM) Client VM (build 1.5.0_06-b05, mixed mode)
              ]]></screen>
            </para>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>using Linux: you must have a X11 graphical interface</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis
              role="bold">384 MB RAM</emphasis>
            for the JVM. That's the default setting, how to change that is described
            <link
              xlink:href="http://directory.apache.org/apacheds/1.5/14-basic-configuration-tasks.html#1.4.Basicconfigurationtasks-MemoryAllocation">here</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section
      id="Download a server installer">
      <title>Download a server installer</title>
      <para>
        We provide native installers for several platforms:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Windows (exe)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Mac OS X (dmg)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Solaris x86 and SPARC (pkg)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Debian package (deb)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>RPM package (rpm)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Linux Binary (bin)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        Additional we provide an zip and tar.gz archive suitable for any platform.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can download them from
        <link
          xlink:href="http://directory.apache.org/apacheds/1.5/downloads.html">here</link>
        .
      </para>
      <para>
        option for people familiar with tools like Subversion and Maven is to built the server from the sources on their
        own. This is described
        <link
          xlink:href="http://directory.apache.org/community%26resources/sources.html">here</link>
        .
      </para>
    </section>
    <section
      id="Installation on Windows">
      <title>Installation on Windows</title>
      <para>Installing can be easily done using the Windows installer. Its interface and functionality is similar to
        other
        wizard based installers.</para>
      <figure
        id="Windows Installer">
        <title>Windows Installer</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="images/Windows_Installer.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        To install the ApacheDS as Windows service you need
        <emphasis
          role="bold">Administrator</emphasis>
        privileges.
      </para>
      <section
        id="Starting and stopping the server Windows">
        <title>Starting and stopping the server</title>
        <para>
          The server can be started and stopped with Windows Services manager (
          <emphasis
            role="bold">Control Panel > Administrative Tools > Services</emphasis>
          ). You must be admin to do this.
        </para>
        <para>From there, you can easily start, stop and restart Apache DS.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section
      id="Installation on Mac OS X">
      <title>Installation on Mac OS X</title>
      <para>To install Apache DS on Mac OS X, simply open the downloaded DMG file and then the "Apache Directory Server
        Installer.pkg" in it.</para>
      <figure
        id="MacOSX Installer">
        <title>MacOSX Installer</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="images/MacOSX_Installer.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>From there, you will be guided to install Apache DS on your system.</para>
      <section
        id="Starting and stopping the server MacOSX">
        <title>Starting and stopping the server</title>
        <para>On Mac OS X, Apache DS is installed as a launchd service and is loaded at startup time (and upon
          successful
          installation).</para>
        <para>You can stop the server by unloading the launchd service with the following command line:</para>
        <code>sudo launchctl unload /Library/LaunchDaemons/org.apache.directory.server.plist</code>
        <para>You can start the server by loading the launchd service with the following command line:</para>
        <code>sudo launchctl load /Library/LaunchDaemons/org.apache.directory.server.plist</code>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section
      id="Installation on Linux and Solaris">
      <title>Installation on Linux and Solaris</title>
      <para>
        The installation for different installers is described on the
        <link
          xlink:href="http://directory.apache.org/apacheds/1.5/downloads.html">Apache Directory Server 1.5 Downloads</link>
        page.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section
    id="Basic configuration tasks">
    <title>Basic configuration tasks</title>
    <section
      id="Changing the server port for LDAP">
      <title>Changing the server port for LDAP</title>
      <para>This section describes how to change to port for the LDAP protocol.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref
              linkend="The task and how to accomplish it" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref
              linkend="Resources_2" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section
        id="The task and how to accomplish it">
        <title>The task and how to accomplish it</title>
        <para>By default the LDAP server listens on port 10389 (unencrypted or StartTLS) and 10636 (SSL). It is quite
          common to run LDAP on 389, which is the well-known port for this protocol. Of course other options are
          imaginable as well. Changing the LDAP port is a good example for adjusting the existing Spring configuration
          as
          introduced in the last section.</para>
        <para>
          Just pick the "ldapServer"-bean from the server.xml file
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
  <ldapServer id="ldapServer"
            ...>
    <transports>
      <tcpTransport address="0.0.0.0" port="10389" nbThreads="8" backLog="50" enableSSL="false"/>
      <tcpTransport address="localhost" port="10636" enableSSL="true"/>
    </transports>
    ...
  </ldapServer>
          ]]></programlisting>
          and change the values of port to your needs. You have to restart the server afterwards in order to take this
          change effect.
        </para>
        <important>
          Due to traditional Unix security restrictions, ports less than 1024 were "trusted". Thus on a
          Unix-System, a
          non-root process must listen on a port greater than 1023.
        </important>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Resources_1">
        <title>Resources</title>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <xref
                linkend="Configuration Parameters Reference" />
              : A Description of all configuration parameters in
              <emphasis>server.xml</emphasis>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Changing the admin password</title>
      <para>This section describes the steps necessary to change the administrator password. Follow the instructions
        provided here step by step.</para>

      <section
        id="Step one: Changing the value in the system partition">
        <title>Step one: Changing the value in the system partition</title>
        <para>While the server is up and running, change the value of the userPassword attribute of the admin
          (uid=admin,ou=system) via LDAP. There are several ways to accomplish this task. In the following, we use the
          Eclipse based Apache Directory Studio.</para>
        <para>A new LDAP connection with this tool is created via "New Connection ..." from the Connections view. Enter
          your connection data in the first step ...</para>
        <figure
          id="New LDAP Connection">
          <title>New LDAP Connection</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="images/NewLDAPConnection1.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>... and in the next step, enter the admin DN uid=admin,ou=system and the current password (default is
          "secret"). Saving the password is not necessary, we will change it anyway. </para>
        <figure
          id="New LDAP Connection 2">
          <title>New LDAP Connection 2</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="images/NewLDAPConnection2.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          Click
          <emphasis>Finish</emphasis>
          to establish the connection.
        </para>
        <para>
          Afterwards, modify the value of the
          <emphasis>userPassword</emphasis>
          attribute of the entry
          <emphasis>uid=admin,ou=system</emphasis>
          . Navigate to the entry in the DIT (
          <emphasis>LDAP Browser</emphasis>
          view), and double click the attribute in the Entry Editor view:
        </para>
        <figure
          id="Entry Editor">
          <title>Entry Editor</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="images/entryEditor.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>The Password Editor dialog shows up; enter the new password. You can optionally select a hash algorithm
          like
          SHA. In this case, the password will be stored one-way encrypted in the attribute value – not a bad idea.
        </para>
        <figure
          id="Password Editor">
          <title>Password Editor</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="images/passwordEditor.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          Pressing
          <emphasis>OK</emphasis>
          stores the new value. Close the connection and shutdown the server.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Step two: Verification">
        <title>Step two: Verification</title>
        <para>
          Verify that you can login as admin with the new password. With Apache Directory Studio, you can change the
          properties of the existing connection profile via a right click in the
          <emphasis>Connections</emphasis>
          view and a selection of the
          <emphasis>Properties</emphasis>
          menu item. The following dialog appears:
        </para>
        <figure
          id="Connection Properties">
          <title>Connection Properties</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="images/connectionProperties.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          Enter the new password and press
          <emphasis>OK</emphasis>
          . Establishing a connection should now work.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Resources_2">
        <title>Resources</title>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <link
                xlink:href="http://directory.apache.org/studio/">Apache Directory Studio</link>
              : The tool used in steps 1 and 2
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section
      id="Adding your own partition resp. suffix">
      <title>Adding your own partition resp. suffix</title>
      <para>This section describes how to add your own data partition.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref
              linkend="What are partitions?" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref
              linkend="Minimal partition definition" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref
              linkend="Adding a partition programmatically" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref
              linkend="More configuration options for a JDBM partition" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section
        id="What are partitions?">
        <title>What are partitions?</title>
        <para>In ApacheDS entries are stored in partitions. Each partition contains a complete entry tree, also referred
          to as a DIT. Multiple partitions may exist and the entry trees they contain are disconnected from each other,
          meaning that changes to entries in partition A would never affect entries in partition B. The entries in a
          particular partition are stored below some naming context called the partition suffix.</para>
        <para>
          The default implementation of partitions is based on
          <link
            xlink:href="http://jdbm.sourceforge.net/">JDBM</link>
          B+Trees (but it's possible to add custom partition implementations). The ApacheDS default configuration
          contains a a data partition with the suffix "dc=example,dc=com". The image below shows the suffixes of a
          freshly installed ApacheDS within Apache Directory Studio.
        </para>
        <figure
          id="Partitions in Studio after install">
          <title>Partitions in Studio after install</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="images/partitions_in_studio_after_install.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>The schema subsystem and ApacheDS itself store their information in special partitions, "ou=schema" and
          "ou=system" respectively.</para>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Minimal partition definition">
        <title>Minimal partition definition</title>
        <para>For the examples in the following sections, we want to add a partition with the suffix "o=sevenSeas". This
          requires editing of the server.xml file, and injecting a first entry, associated with the root of this
          partition (here, "o=sevenseas") .</para>
        <para>
          Open the
          <emphasis>server.xml</emphasis>
          file for your directory instance in your favorite editor and look for the following element with name
          partitions.
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
 <partitions>
  ...
  <jdbmPartition id="example" cacheSize="100" suffix="dc=example,dc=com" optimizerEnabled="true"
                 syncOnWrite="true">
    <indexedAttributes>
    ...
    </indexedAttributes>
  </jdbmPartition>
 </partitions>
...
        ]]></programlisting>
        <para>
          Save the
          <emphasis>server.xml</emphasis>
          file and restart the server. The server has a new suffix now, but no context entry has been created for it. If
          you connect with an LDAP Browser (Apache Directory Studio for instance), the partition is only visible in the
          Root DSE. Below the Entry Editor of Directory Studio for the Root DSE after connecting to an ApacheDS instance
          configured like above.
        </para>
        <figure
          id="Root DSE">
          <title>Root DSE</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="images/root_dse.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Before using the partition (e.g. adding entries), you have to add a context entry. If you plan to load
          LDIF data to your partition anyway, simply provide the context entry (the "root" of your partition) as a first
          data set. In our example it might look like this:</para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
dn: o=sevenSeas
o: sevenSeas
objectClass: top
objectClass: organization
description: The context entry for suffix o=sevenSeas
        ]]>
        </programlisting>
        <para>It is also possible to import a file to ApacheDS which only contains such an entry, of cause. Here is an
          example on how to procede for the seven seas :</para>
        <para>In the LDAP Browser of Directory Studio, right click on the DIT entry and select "Import -> LDIF
          Import...". A file selections dialog appears. Browse to the LDIF file and click Finish. The entry (or entries,
          if you provide more of them) will be added to to partition.</para>
        <para>
          The following image depicts the partitions after reconnecting with Apache Directory Studio (
          <emphasis>LDAP Browser</emphasis>
          view).
        </para>
        <figure
          id="Partitions in Studio after adding">
          <title>Partitions in Studio after adding</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="images/partitions_in_studio_after_adding.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Loading the context entry automatically on startup">
        <title>Loading the context entry automatically on startup</title>
        <para>
          If you don't want to launch Apache Studio, or to inject the LDIF file using a command line tool, you can
          also
          tells the server to load the file when it will be laucnhed the first time. Just create a ldif file
          containing
          the context entry, and add some tag into the
          <emphasis>server.xml</emphasis>
          file. For instance, you have created the
          <emphasis
            role="bold">sevenSeasRoot.ldif</emphasis>
          file containing
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
# SevenSeas root context entry
dn: o=sevenSeas
o: sevenSeas
objectClass: top
objectClass: organization
description: The context entry for suffix o=sevenSeas
        ]]></programlisting>
        <para>
          Now just modify the
          <emphasis>server.xml</emphasis>
          file to add this line :
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
  <apacheDS id="apacheDS"
            synchPeriodMillis="15000"
            allowAnonymousAccess="false">

    <directoryService>#directoryService</directoryService>

     We load the SevenSeas root context entry here 
    <ldifDirectory>sevenSeasRoot.ldif</ldifDirectory>
...
        ]]></programlisting>
        <para>The contextEntry will be loaded when the server will be started the first time.</para>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Adding a partition programmatically">
        <title>Adding a partition programmatically</title>
        <para>The same o=sevenseas partition can be created through the application code using the Partition and
          DirectoryService API</para>
        <para>Here is the sample code to create a new partition o=sevenseas and its context entry programmatically
        </para>
        <example
          id="Sample code to create a new partition">
          <title>Sample code to create a new partition</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
JdbmPartition sevenseasPartition = new JdbmPartition();
sevenseasPartition.setId("sevenseas");
sevenseasPartition.setSuffix("o=sevenseas");
sevenseasPartition.setCacheSize(1000);
sevenseasPartition.init(directoryService);

// Create some indices (optional)
Set<Index<?,ServerEntry>> indexedAttrs = new HashSet<Index<?, ServerEntry>>();
indexedAttrs.add( new JdbmIndex<Object, ServerEntry>("objectClass"));
indexedAttrs.add( new JdbmIndex<Object, ServerEntry>("o"));
sevenseasPartition.setIndexedAttributes( indexedAttrs );

//Add partition to the directory service
directoryService.addPartition(sevenseasPartition);

// start the directory service
directoryService.startup();

// create the context entry
ServerEntry entry = new DefaultServerEntry( directoryService.getRegistries(), new LdapDN( "o=sevenseas") );
entry.put( "objectClass",  "top", "organization" );
entry.put("o","sevenseas");

// add the context entry
AddContextPartitionOperationContext adOpContext = new AddContextPartitionOperationContext( directoryService.getAdminSession(), sevenseasPartition );
adOpContext.add( entry, null );
directoryService.getPartitionNexus().addContextPartition( adOpContext );
      ]]></programlisting>
        </example>
      </section>
      <section
        id="More configuration options for a JDBM partition">
        <title>More configuration options for a JDBM partition</title>
        <para>Here is a list of the used attributes, their default values and meaning</para>
        <table
          id="More configuration options for a JDBM partition table">
          <title>More configuration options for a JDBM partition</title>
          <tgroup
            cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Property</entry>
                <entry>Default value</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>id</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>(required) uniquely identifies the partition</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>suffix</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>(required) an LDAP DN ("dc=example, dc=com", for instance)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>cacheSize</entry>
                <entry>-1</entry>
                <entry>cache size expressed as a number of entries</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>optimizerEnabled</entry>
                <entry>true</entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>syncOnWrite</entry>
                <entry>true</entry>
                <entry>sync disks on every write operation</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section
      id="Configure logging">
      <title>Configure logging</title>
      <para>In order to detect and analyze problems, adjusting the log level of a server can be a valuable tool. This
        section describes how to configure logging within a standalone ApacheDS.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref
              linkend="ApacheDS and logging" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref
              linkend="Default behavior after installation" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref
              linkend="Adjusting logging to your needs" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref
              linkend="Example configurations" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref
              linkend="Log settings of the Windows daemon process" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref
              linkend="Resources logging" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section
        id="ApacheDS and logging">
        <title>ApacheDS and logging</title>
        <para>
          ApacheDS 1.5 uses
          <link
            xlink:href="http://www.slf4j.org/">SLF4J</link>
          as its logging solution. This is a simple facade for various logging APIs. The default for ApacheDS 1.5 is
          <link
            xlink:href="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/">log4j</link>
          .
        </para>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Default behavior after installation">
        <title>Default behavior after installation</title>
        <para>
          By default, ApacheDS writes log files in the directory
          <emphasis>&lt;APACHDS_HOME&gt;/var/log/</emphasis>
          . Besides stdout, a
          <link
            xlink:href="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/docs/api/org/apache/log4j/RollingFileAppender.html">RollingFileAppender</link>
          is used to collect warnings and errors. It
          backups the log files when they reach a certain size.
        </para>
        <para>
          Here is what the default configuration file
          <emphasis>log4j.properties</emphasis>
          , which is located in
          <emphasis>&lt;APACHDS_HOME&gt;/conf/</emphasis>
          , looks like.
          The name of the RollingFileAppender is "R":
        </para>
        <example
          id="Configuration RollingFileAppender">
          <title>Configuration RollingFileAppender</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
log4j.rootCategory=WARN, stdout, R

log4j.appender.stdout=org.apache.log4j.ConsoleAppender
log4j.appender.stdout.layout=org.apache.log4j.PatternLayout

log4j.appender.R=org.apache.log4j.RollingFileAppender
log4j.appender.R.File=apacheds-rolling.log

log4j.appender.R.MaxFileSize=1024KB
# Keep some backup files
log4j.appender.R.MaxBackupIndex=5

log4j.appender.R.layout=org.apache.log4j.PatternLayout
log4j.appender.R.layout.ConversionPattern=[%d{HH:mm:ss}] %p [%c] - %m%n

log4j.appender.stdout.layout.ConversionPattern=[%d{HH:mm:ss}] %p [%c] - %m%n

# with these we'll not get innundated when switching to DEBUG
log4j.logger.org.apache.directory.shared.ldap.name=WARN
log4j.logger.org.springframework=WARN
log4j.logger.org.apache.directory.shared.codec=WARN
log4j.logger.org.apache.directory.shared.asn1=WARN
        ]]>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>In this file "R" is configured like this:</para>
        <table
          id="Configuration RollingFileAppender table">
          <title>Configuration RollingFileAppender</title>
          <tgroup
            cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Property name</entry>
                <entry>Value in file above</entry>
                <entry>Meaning</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>File</entry>
                <entry>apacheds-rolling.log</entry>
                <entry>
                  path to the output log file, in our case relative to
                  <emphasis>var/log</emphasis>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>MaxFileSize</entry>
                <entry>1024KB</entry>
                <entry>maximum size that the output file is allowed to reach before being rolled over to backup files
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>MaxBackupIndex</entry>
                <entry>5</entry>
                <entry>number of backup files kept</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>ConversionPattern</entry>
                <entry>[%d{HH:mm:ss}] %p [%c] - %m%n</entry>
                <entry>format string for logging events</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>If the default logging does not meet your requirements, you can easily adjust the configuration to your
          needs.</para>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Adjusting logging to your needs">
        <title>Adjusting logging to your needs</title>
        <section
          id="Log file location (where the log files are placed)">
          <title>Log file location (where the log files are placed)</title>
          <para>
            By default the log files are placed at
            <emphasis>&lt;APACHDS_HOME&gt;/var/log/</emphasis>
            , but that can be changed.
          </para>
          <section
            id="Linux/MacOS/Solaris">
            <title>Linux/MacOS/Solaris</title>
            <para>
              On this systems the location of the log files is configured via an entry in
              <emphasis
                role="bold">/bin/server.init</emphasis>
              . Look for the following lines and change it to your preferences:
            </para>
            <example>
              <title>Log file location Linux/MacOS/Solaris</title>
              <screen><![CDATA[
$DAEMON_HOME/apacheds \
...
-outfile $SERVER_HOME/var/log/apacheds-stdout.log \
-errfile $SERVER_HOME/var/log/apacheds-stderr.log \
...    
$APACHEDS_HOME start
              ]]></screen>
            </example>
          </section>
          <section
            id="Windows">
            <title>Windows</title>
            <para>
              On Windows you can use the configuration wizard for the service as shown in the screenshot above. To
              adjust the log path you have to adjust the values of
              <emphasis
                role="bold">Redirect Stdout</emphasis>
              and
              <emphasis
                role="bold">Redirect Stderror</emphasis>
              .
            </para>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section
          id="Log level (how detailed the logs are)">
          <title>Log level (how detailed the logs are)</title>
          <para>The following log levels from log4j are used for messages within ApacheDS:</para>
          <table
            id="Log level">
            <title>Log level</title>
            <tgroup
              cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Level</entry>
                  <entry>Description from log4j documentation</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>DEBUG</entry>
                  <entry>designates fine-grained informational events that are most useful to debug an application
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>INFO</entry>
                  <entry>designates informational messages that highlight the progress of the application at
                    coarse-grained
                    level</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>WARN</entry>
                  <entry>designates potentially harmful situations</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>ERROR</entry>
                  <entry>designates error events that might still allow the application to continue running</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>FATAL</entry>
                  <entry>designates very severe error events that will presumably lead the application to abort </entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
          <para>
            The default (global) log level in the configuration is
            <emphasis>WARN</emphasis>
            . All messages of level WARN and more severe (ERROR, FATAL) are written to the rolling log file. The easiest
            way to get finer log messages is to change it like this
          </para>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
log4j.rootCategory=DEBUG, stdout, R
...
          ]]></programlisting>
          <para>detailed log messages took much file space and time and therefore should only be enabled globally in
            order to analyze problems.</para>
          <para>is possible to configure the logging more fine grained by using categories. Within the default
            configuration there are some examples:</para>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
# with these we'll not get innundated when switching to DEBUG
log4j.logger.org.apache.directory.shared.ldap.name=WARN
log4j.logger.org.springframework=WARN
log4j.logger.org.apache.directory.shared.codec=WARN
log4j.logger.org.apache.directory.shared.asn1=WARN
          ]]></programlisting>
          <para>
            If the global level is switched to DEBUG, these definitions override the setting with WARN for certain areas
            and therefore keep the file a little bit smaller. Learn more about the concept of categories in the
            <link
              xlink:href="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/docs/manual.html">Short introduction to log4j</link>
            .
          </para>
        </section>
        <section
          id="Format for log messages">
          <title>Format for log messages</title>
          <para>
            The format of each line within a log file is controlled by a pattern. For the
            <emphasis>RollingFileAppender</emphasis>
            in the default configuration it looks like this
          </para>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
log4j.appender.R.layout=org.apache.log4j.PatternLayout
log4j.appender.R.layout.ConversionPattern=[%d{HH:mm:ss}] %p [%c] - %m%n
...
        ]]></programlisting>
          <para>Some examples lines within the log file, formatted with the pattern "[%d{HH:mm:ss}] %p [%c] - %m%n" are:
          </para>
          <screen><![CDATA[
...
[12:29:03] WARN [org.apache.directory.server.core.DefaultDirectoryService]
    - You didn't change the admin password of directory service instance 'default'.
    Please update the admin password as soon as possible to prevent a possible security breach.
...
[12:29:05] INFO [org.apache.directory.server.jndi.ServerContextFactory]
    - Successful bind of an LDAP Service (636) is complete.
[12:29:05] INFO [org.apache.directory.server.Service] - server: started in 6750 milliseconds
...
        ]]></screen>
          <para>The pattern uses the following conversion characters:</para>
          <table
            id="Log file output patterns">
            <title>Log file output patterns</title>
            <tgroup
              cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Character</entry>
                  <entry>Outputs</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>%d</entry>
                  <entry>date of the logging event in the given format. like "12:29:05" for %d{HH:mm:ss}</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>%p</entry>
                  <entry>priority (level) of the logging event, like "INFO" or "WARN"</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>%c</entry>
                  <entry>category of the logging event, like "org.apache.directory.server.Service"</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>%m</entry>
                  <entry>application supplied message associated with the logging event</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>%n</entry>
                  <entry>platform dependent line separator</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
          <para>
            The
            <link
              xlink:href="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/docs/api/org/apache/log4j/PatternLayout.html">javadoc of log4j</link>
            contains a table with all valid %-characters and their meaning.
          </para>
          <para>
            Simple adjust the pattern in the
            <emphasis>log4j.properties</emphasis>
            file to get the log format of your choice, for instance
          </para>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
log4j.appender.R.layout.ConversionPattern=[%d{dd.MM.yyyy HH:mm:ss}] %p: %c{1}.%M() - %m%n
          ]]></programlisting>
          <para>leads to messages of this form:</para>
          <screen><![CDATA[
...
[29.12.2006 13:50:44] INFO: ServerContextFactory.startLDAP0() 
    - Successful bind of an LDAP Service (636) is complete.
[29.12.2006 13:50:44] INFO: Service.init() - server: started in 3016 milliseconds
...
          ]]></screen>
          <warning>
            <para>"Generating caller location information like with %M or %L is extremely slow. Its use should be
              avoided unless execution speed is not an issue." (from the log4j documentation)</para>
          </warning>
        </section>
        <section
          id="Advanced log4j configuration">
          <title>Advanced log4j configuration</title>
          <para>
            You can take advantage of other features of log4j as well, such as other appenders like the daily
            rolling
            file appender. And you can configure logging to make it easier for you to view the messages with
            tools like
            Log Factor 5 or
            <link
              xlink:href="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/docs/chainsaw.html">Chainsaw</link>
            .
          </para>
          <para>
            Learn more about log4j and related tools at its
            <link
              xlink:href="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/docs/index.html">homepage</link>
            .
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Example configurations">
        <title>Example configurations</title>
        <para>The following example could be used to log all incoming search, add, delete, modify and moddn requests:
        </para>
        <example
          id="Example log4j configuration">
          <title>Example log4j.properties configuration</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
log4j.logger.org.apache.directory.server.ldap.handlers.SearchHandler=DEBUG
log4j.logger.org.apache.directory.server.ldap.handlers.AddHandler=DEBUG
log4j.logger.org.apache.directory.server.ldap.handlers.DeleteHandler=DEBUG
log4j.logger.org.apache.directory.server.ldap.handlers.ModifyHandler=DEBUG
log4j.logger.org.apache.directory.server.ldap.handlers.ModifyDnHandler=DEBUG
        ]]></programlisting>
        </example>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Log settings of the Windows daemon process">
        <title>Log settings of the Windows daemon process</title>
        <para>After installation on Windows, you have the option to configure the ApacheDS Windows Service (you can do
          this later as well). If you do so, one option pane is dedicated to logging:</para>
        <figure
          id="W32 Service Properties">
          <title>W32 Service Properties</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="images/w32_service_properties.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>You can adjust the logging level and a log path. Note that this is for the daemon only. The server itself
          is configured as described above.</para>
      </section>
      <section
        id="Resources logging">
        <title>Resources</title>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <link
                xlink:href="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/docs/manual.html">Short introduction to log4j</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section
      id="Enable and disable anonymous access">
      <title>Enable and disable anonymous access</title>
      <para>This section briefly describes how to enable and disable anonymous access.</para>
      <para>Anonymous access to the server is enabled by default. This includes read and write access! </para>
      <para>
        If you use the server standalone configured with a
        <emphasis>server.xml</emphasis>
        file, you can disable anonymous binds by
        changing the value for property
        <emphasis>allowAnonymousAccess</emphasis>
        in the Spring bean definition for bean
        <emphasis>defaultDirectoryService</emphasis>
        , as depicted in the following fragment:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
  <defaultDirectoryService id="directoryService" instanceId="default"
                           ...
                           allowAnonymousAccess="false"
                           ...>
        ]]></programlisting>
      <para>A restart of the server is necessary for this change to take effect. Afterwards, all clients have to provide
        their name (distinguished name) and password in order to bind to the directory service.</para>
      <para>
        Learn more about authentication option in the corresponding section of this guide
        <xref
          linkend="Authentication options">here</xref>
        .
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section
    id="About the sample configurations and sample directory data">
    <title>About the sample configurations and sample directory data</title>
    <para>This section describes basic parameters used throughout the examples in this guide. It also introduces the
      sample directory "Sailors of the seven seas", and other requisites you need.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="Basic server parameters" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="LDAP Clients" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="The sample data (Sailors of the seven seas)" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <xref
            linkend="Resources RFC 2849" />
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section
      id="Basic server parameters">
      <title>Basic server parameters</title>
      <para>In the following sections we assume that you will install, configure and run Apache Directory Server on a
        host with the following host name using the parameters given in the following table:</para>
      <table
        id="Basic server parameters table">
        <title>Basic server parameters</title>
        <tgroup
          cols="2">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Parameter name</entry>
              <entry>Parameter value</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Hostname</entry>
              <entry>zanzibar</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Port</entry>
              <entry>10389</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Suffix ("Base DN")</entry>
              <entry>o=sevenSeas</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Admin user DN</entry>
              <entry>uid=admin,ou=system</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Admin user password</entry>
              <entry>secret</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
        Before you start playing with the data make sure that you have added a partition with the suffix o=sevenSeas to
        the server. How to do this is described
        <xref
          linkend="Basic configuration tasks">here</xref>
        .
      </para>
      <para>In order to increase recognition, all examples of the Basic User's Guide use these values. Adjust them to
        your needs (especially the password).</para>
    </section>
    <section
      id="LDAP Clients">
      <title>LDAP Clients</title>
      <para>LDAP is a client/server protocol. Hence you need an LDAP client to connect remotely to the Apache Directory
        Server (or at least the directory part of it, to be precise). There are different options here. Because the
        protocol is standardized, you may use every LDAP compliant client. This is comparable to HTTP, where you can use
        each web browser to communicate with virtually each web server, and totally different to relational databases.
        The latter have a (more or less) standardized query language (SQL), but vendors tend to use individual network
        access protocols. In practice, the LDAP situation is even better than HTTP, because there were no LDAP browser
        wars ...</para>
      <para>Many software components may act as an LDAP client. Normally they use LDAP libraries to connect. In the
        following sections you meet LDAP clients with GUI and LDAP command line tools. Some Java programming examples
        which takes advantage of JNDI are provided as well.</para>
      <para>In other sections you will learn how E-Mail clients like Mozilla Thunderbird and application servers like
        Apache Tomcat connect to Apache Directory server, either to use the data stored in the directory (e.g. mail
        addresses) or to perform authentication and authorization.</para>
      <para>
        Recapitulating the Basic User's Guide describes connecting to the server with tools provided by ApacheDS as well
        as third party products. In all cases the examples will use the connection data depicted above (
        <emphasis>ldap://zanzibar:10389/o=sevenSeas</emphasis>
        )
      </para>
    </section>
    <section
      id="The sample data (Sailors of the seven seas)">
      <title>The sample data (Sailors of the seven seas)</title>
      <para>
        The file
        <link
          xlink:href="data/apache_ds_tutorial.ldif">apache_ds_tutorial.ldif</link>
        contains some sample data, which is used in the following sections. It is a
        text file in the so called
        <emphasis
          role="bold">LDIF</emphasis>
        format. LDIF stands for LDAP Data Interchange Format. It is widely adopted in
        the LDAP world and standardized in
        <link
          xlink:href="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc2849.html">RFC 2849</link>
        . Therefore you are able to import our sample data into other
        directory solutions as well, not only into Apache
        Directory Server.
      </para>
      <para>The sample directory tree contains entries for persons and groups. These are structured in sub trees
        (ou=people and ou=groups), see image below. The person entries describe sailors (historic and fictional), the
        group entries bundle them. An example for a group is the ship crew of HMS Bounty.</para>
      <figure
        id="Sample LDAP tree structure">
        <title>Sample LDAP tree structure</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="images/sample_structure.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>This snippet of the file represents a single entry, just to give you an impression of how LDIF files look
        like.</para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
# Entry for Fletcher Christian
#
dn: cn=Fletcher Christian,ou=people,o=sevenSeas
cn: Fletcher Christian
objectClass: top
objectClass: person
objectClass: organizationalPerson
objectClass: inetOrgPerson
sn: Christian
givenName: Fletcher
description: Lieutenant Fletcher Christian
manager: cn=William Bligh,ou=people,o=sevenSeas
...
        ]]></programlisting>
      <para>There are different ways to import the data. Generally perform the following steps:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Download and install the server, described im
            <xref
              linkend="Installing and starting the server" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Configure a partition for the sample date, described in
            <xref
              linkend="Basic configuration tasks" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Import the data, for instance using
            <link
              xlink:href="http://directory.apache.org/studio/">Apache Directory Studio</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section
      id="Resources RFC 2849">
      <title>Resources</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link
              xlink:href="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc2849.html">RFC 2849</link>
            The LDAP Data Interchange Format (LDIF) – Technical Specification
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
