<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="jmachols@apache.org">Jeff Machols</author>
    <title>Apache Directory Project: LDAP Common Code</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>
    <section name="Overview">
      <p>LDAP Common Code</p>
      <p> 
      This project contains code and utilities common to the LDAP protocol.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="LDAP Common Packages">
      <subsection name="Filter">
        <p>
          The filter package will parsese and LDAP expression into 
          a filter expression tree as defined in <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2254.txt">RFC 2254</a>
        </p>  
      </subsection>
        
      <subsection name="LDIF">
        <p>
          The The LDAP Data Interchange Format (LDIF) parsing 
          package Parses an LDIF into a multimap or a JNDI 
          Attributes instance of attribute key/value pairs with 
          potential more than one attribute value per attribute.  
          This parser populates the MultiMap or Attributes 
          instance with all attributes within the LDIF including 
          control attributes like the 'dn' and the changeType.
        </p>
        <p>
          The package contain an LDIF entry class that can be used.  Along
          with the parsing utility, the embedding application can LDIF
          parsing and management without becomming an expert on the RFC.
          Addition details about LDIF can be obtained from the 
          <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2849.txt">LDIF RFC</a>
        </p>        
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Message">
      	<p>
          The LDAP Common Messaging package provides a framework for
          all LDAP request and response messages.  Each of the reponses
          and requests have an implementation.
      	</p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Name">
        <p>
          This package provides LDAP distinguished name creation and 
          normalization.  This provides a common method for ensuring 
          you are creating the entry DN correctly.  Failure to properly
          create and normalize the DN of an entry will result in unpredicatble
          results when operations are performed on the entry.  
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
    </section>
  </body>
</document>