<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="akarasulu">akarasulu</author>
    
  </properties>
  <body>
    <p>
ApacheDS uses an adaptation of the X.500 basic access control scheme in
combination with X.500 subentries to control access to entries and attributes
within the DIT. This document will show you how to enable the basic access
control mechanism and how to define access control information to manage access
to protected
resources.</p>
    <section heading="h2" name="Enabling Basic Access Controls">
      <p>
By default the access control subsystem is turned off. Once enabled everything
is tightly locked down. Only the special admin user, '*uid=admin,ou=system*', is
not affected by permissions. Access to all operations are denied by default
until enabled using an ACIItem. For this reason enabling basic access controls
is a configuration
option.</p>
      <p>
To turn on the basic access control mechanism you need to set the
*accessControlEnabled* property in the configuration to true. This can be set
programatically on the StartupConfiguration or via the
server.xml.</p>
    </section>
    <section heading="h2" name="Types of ACI (Access Control Information)">
      <p>
Three different types of ACI exist. All types use the same specification syntax
for an ACIITem. These types differ in their placement and manner of use within
the
directory.</p>
      <subsection heading="h3" name="Entry ACI">
        <p>
Entry ACI are access controls added to entries to protect that entry
specifically. Meaning the protoected entry is the entry where the ACI resides.
When performing an operation on an entry, ApacheDS checks for the presence of
the multivalued operational attribute, *entryACI*. The values of the entryACI
attribute contain
ACIItems.</p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <img src="http://docs.safehaus.org/images/icons/emoticons/warning.png"/>
            </td>
            <td>
              <p>
There is one exception to the rule of consulting entryACI attributes within
ApacheDS: add operations do not consult the entryACI within the entry being
added. This is a security precaution. If allowed users can arbitrarily add
entries where they wanted by putting entryACI into the new entry being added.
This could comprimise the
DSA.</p>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </subsection>
      <subsection heading="h3" name="Prescriptive ACI">
        <p>
Prescriptive ACI are access controls that are applied to a collection of
entries, not just to a single entry. Collections of entries are defined by the
subtreeSpecifications of subentries. Hence prescriptive ACI are added to
subentries as attributes and are applied by ApacheDS to the entries selected by
the subentry's subtreeSpecification. ApacheDS uses the *prescriptiveACI*
multivalued operational attribute within subentries to contain ACIItems that
apply to the entry
collection.</p>
        <p>
Prescriptive ACI can save much effort when trying to control access to a
collection of resources. Prescriptive ACI can even be specified to apply access
controls to entries that do not yet exist within the DIT. They are a very
powerful mechanism and for this reason they are the prefered mechanism for
managing access to protected resources. ApacheDS is optimized specifically for
managing access to collections of entries rather than point entries
themselves.</p>
        <p>
Users should try to avoid entry ACIs whenever possible, and use prescriptive
ACIs instead. Entry ACIs are more for managing exceptional cases and should not
be used
excessively.</p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>
              <img src="http://docs.safehaus.org/images/icons/emoticons/information.png"/>
            </th>
            <th>
              <center>How it works!</center>
            </th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td/>
            <td>
              <p>
For every type of LDAP operation ApacheDS checks to see if any access control
subentries include the protected entry in their collection. The set of
subentries which include the protected entry are discovered very rapidly by the
subentry subsystem. The subentry subsystem caches subtreeSpecifications for all
subentries within the server so inclusion checks are
fast.</p>
              <p>
For each access control subentry in the set, ApacheDS checks within a
prescriptive ACI cache for ACI tuples. ApacheDS also caches prescriptive ACI
information in a special form called ACI tuples. This is done so ACIItem parsing
and conversion to an optimal representations for evaluation is not required at
access time. This way access based on prescriptive ACIs is determined very
rapidly.</p>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </subsection>
      <subsection heading="h3" name="Subentry ACI">
        <p>
Access to subentries also needs to be controlled. Subentries are special in
ApacheDS. Although they subordinate to an administrative entry (entry of an
Administrative Point), they are technically considered to be in the same context
as their administrative entry. ApacheDS considers the perscriptive ACI applied
to the administrative entry, to also apply to its
subentries.</p>
        <p>
This however is not the most intuitive mechanism to use for explicitly
controlling access to subentries. A more explicit mechanism is used to specify
ACIs specifically for protecting subentries. ApacheDS uses the multivalued
operational attribute, *subentryACI*, within administrative entries to control
access to immediately subordinate
subentries.</p>
        <p>
Protection policies for ACIs themselves can be managed within the entry of an
administrative
point.</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    <section heading="h2" name="Some Simple Examples">
      <p>
The ACIItem syntax is very expressive and that makes it extremely powerful for
specifying complex access control policies. However the syntax is not very easy
to grasp for beginners. For this reason we start with simple examples that focus
on different protection mechanisms offered by the ACIItem syntax. We do this
instead of specifying the grammar which is not the best way to learn a
language.</p>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>
            <img src="http://docs.safehaus.org/images/icons/emoticons/forbidden.png"/>
          </th>
          <th>
            <center>Before you go any further...</center>
          </th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td/>
          <td>
            <p>
Please don't go any further until you have read up on the use
of
              <a href="./subentries.html">Subentries</a>
. Knowledge of subentries, subtreeSpecifications, administrative areas, and
administrative roles are required to properly digest the following
matterial.
            </p>
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>
      <p>
Before going on to these trails you might want to set up an Administrative Area
for managing access control via prescriptiveACI.  Both subentryACI and
prescriptiveACI require the presence of an Administrative Point entry.  For more
information and code examples
see
        <a href="./acareas.html">ACAreas</a>
.
      </p>
      <subsection heading="h3" name="ACI Trails">
        <p>
Here are some trails that resemble simple HOWTO guides.  They're ordered with
the most pragmatic usage first.  We will add to these trails over
time.</p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>
Trail</th>
            <th>
Description</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="./enablesearchforallusers.html">EnableSearchForAllUsers</a>
            </td>
            <td>
Enabling access to browse and read all entries and their attributes by
authenticated
users.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="./denysubentryaccess.html">DenySubentryAccess</a>
            </td>
            <td>
Protecting access to subentries
themselves.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="./allowselfpasswordmodify.html">AllowSelfPasswordModify</a>
            </td>
            <td>
Granting users the rights needed to change their own
passwords.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="./grantadddelmodtogroup.html">GrantAddDelModToGroup</a>
            </td>
            <td>
Granting add, delete, and modify permissions to a group of
users.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="./grantmodtoentry.html">GrantModToEntry</a>
            </td>
            <td>
Applying ACI to a single
entry.</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
