<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
      <author email="akarasulu@apache.org">Alex Karasulu</author>
      <author email="erodriguez@apache.org">Enrique Rodriguez</author>
    <title>Overview</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Introduction">
      <p>The Kerberos provider for ApacheDS implements <a
        href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1510.txt">RFC 1510</a> the Kerberos V5 Network
        Authentication Service. The purpose of Kerberos is to verify the identities of
        principals (users or services) on an unprotected network. While generally thought
        of as a single-sign-on technology, Kerberos' true strength is in authenticating
        users without ever sending their password over the network. Kerberos is designed
        for use on open (untrusted) networks and, therefore, operates under the assumption
        that packets traveling along the network can be read, modified, and inserted at
        will. <a
        href="http://www.computerworld.com/computerworld/records/images/pdf/kerberos_chart.pdf">This
        chart</a> provides a good description of the protocol workflow.</p>
      <p>Kerberos is named for the three-headed dog that guards the gates to Hades. The three
        heads are the client, the Kerberos server, and the network service being
        accessed.</p>
      <p>The ApacheDS Kerberos provider is implemented as a protocol-provider plugin.
        As a plugin, the Kerberos provider leverages Apache Directory's MINA for front-end
        services and the Apache Directory read-optimized backing store via JNDI for
        persistent directory services.</p>
      <p>The Kerberos provider for ApacheDS, in conjunction with MINA and the ApacheDS
        store, provides an easy-to-use yet fully-featured network authentication service.
        As implemented within the Apache Directory, the Kerberos provider will provide:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Authentication service (RFC 1510)</li>
        <li>Ticket-granting service (RFC 1510)</li>
        <li>Pre-authentication support (RFC 1510)</li>
        <li>DES encryption systems (RFC 1510)</li>
        <li>Triple-DES (DES3) encryption systems</li>
        <li>LDAP/JMX management</li>
        <li>UDP and TCP Support (MINA)</li>
        <li>Traffic throttling (MINA)</li>
        <li>Overload shielding (MINA)</li>
        <li>Easy POJO embeddability for containers such as Geronimo, JBoss, and OSGi</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
