<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="akarasulu@apache.org">Alex Karasulu</author>
    <title>Apache Directory Project: Eve's Features</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>
    <section name="Eve's Features">
      <p> 
        The Eve Directory Server is an embeddable LDAP server implemented in 
        pure Java.  It has several features that make it unique amoung LDAP 
        servers.  These features are described below:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>
          Designed as an LDAP and X.500 experimentation platform.  Plugable
          components and subsystems make Eve extremely modular and perfect for
          experiments with various aspects of the LDAP and X.500 protocols.  Eve
          can run on any IoC based microkernel using IoC type wrappers for her
          components.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Eve's frontend is completely separable from its backend and 
          vice-versa making it very conducive for implementing virtual 
          directories and front ends to X.500.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Several backends can be implemented and plugged into Eve's backend
          nexus.  Eve will initially support a custom JDBM and JDBC based 
          backend but any backend can be implemented so long as it conforms to
          the backend SPI.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Eve exposes all aspects of administration via a special system 
          backend.  LDAP can be used to manage these concerns through the
          system context.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Java and Groovy based triggers and stored procedures are supported 
          by Eve's backend subsystem.  Any backends plugged into the nexus 
          are automatically decorated with these features.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Both Eve's backend and her frontend are embeddable.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Eve implements a server side JNDI LDAP provider as the facade for the 
          entire backend subsystem.  JNDI operations are directly translated by
          this provider into operations against the nexus and the target 
          backend.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Eve uses JNDI as the data access API for stored procedures.  This 
          makes stored procedures functional within and outside of the server
          without requiring recompilation.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Eve is based on a simple Staged Event Driven Architecture (SEDA) which
          gives Eve the ability to handle large amounts of concurrency.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Eve uses the Snickers tools and APIs for ASN.1 BER encoding and 
          decoding.  These tools are designed for a very small encoding and
          decoding footprint as well as for use in non-blocking servers.  The
          revolutionary event based processing of BER messages makes Eve very
          efficient at handling this aspect of the protocol.
        </li>
      </ul>
      </section>
    </body>
</document>