<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="akarasulu@apache.org">Alex Karasulu</author>
    <title>Apache Directory Project: Eve's Features</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>
    <section name="Eve's Features">
      <p> 
        The Eve Directory Server is an embeddable LDAP server implemented in 
        pure Java.  It has several features that make it unique amoung LDAP 
        servers.  These features are described below:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>
          Designed as an LDAP and X.500 experimentation platform.  Plugable
          components and subsystems make Eve extremely modular and perfect for
          experiments with various aspects of the LDAP protocol.  Eve be made to
          can run on any IoC based microkernel using IoC type wrappers for her
          POJO components implementing POJI services.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Eve's frontend is completely separable from its backend and 
          vice-versa making it very flexible for implementing virtual
          directories, proxy servers and gateways to X.500.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Several backends can be implemented and plugged into Eve's partition
          nexus.  Eve will initially support a BTree based partition but any
          backing store can be used to implement a partition so long as it
          conforms to interfaces.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Eve will expose all aspects of administration via a special system
          backend.  LDAP can be used to manage these concerns through the
          system naming context at <code>ou=system</code>.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Java based triggers and stored procedures are being implemented.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Both Eve's backend subsystem and her frontend are separable and
          independently embeddable.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Eve implements a server side JNDI LDAP provider as the facade for the 
          entire backend subsystem.  JNDI operations are directly translated by
          this provider into operations against the nexus and the target 
          partitions storing the entries.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Eve will use JNDI as the data access API for stored procedures.  This
          makes stored procedures functional within and outside of the server
          without requiring recompilation.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Eve's networking code is based on a simple Staged Event Driven
          Architecture (SEDA) which gives Eve the ability to handle large
          amounts of concurrency.  Multiple swapable network layers will be
          available for different usage characteristics.
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Eve uses the Snickers tools and APIs for ASN.1 BER encoding and 
          decoding.  These tools are designed for a very small encoding and
          decoding footprint as well as for use in non-blocking servers.  The
          chunking nature of the BER codec makes Eve very efficient at handling
          this aspect of the protocol and makes her resistant to DoS attacks.
        </li>
      </ul>
      </section>
    </body>
</document>