<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="akarasulu@apache.org">Alex Karasulu</author>
    <title>Eve JNDI Provider</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>
    <section name="Eve JNDI Provider">
      <p>
        Besides an LDAP protocol server, Eve is also a JNDI provider for the
        LDAP namespace.  Unlike the SUN JNDI LDAP Provider which is an LDAP
        client, the Eve JNDI Provider is not.  JNDI operations on Contexts
        directly tap into the server's database partitions to add, lookup,
        alter, and search for entries.  There is nothing done over the wire.
      </p>

      <p>
        Eve leverages its JNDI LDAP provider in several ways.  First stored
        procedures written in Java will naturally use JNDI to alter entries
        using this provider.  Thanks to JNDI the same procedure outside of the
        server can be tested using the SUN JNDI LDAP provider.  This
        transparency is wicked cool making testing easy.  The Eve JNDI provider
        is also used as the API of choice for integrating Eve into other Java
        applications and servers.  The first InitialContext request to the Eve
        provider fires up the entire server.  So you need not learn anything
        new to start playing with her!
      </p>

      <p>
        This document describes the Eve JNDI Provider in terms of the custom
        properties used to control its behavoir in the solid state and for
        configuring her on start up.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Eve Specific JNDI Properties">
      <table>
        <tr><th>key</th><th>optional</th><th>description</th></tr>
        <tr>
          <td>eve.wkdir</td>
          <td>true</td>
          <td>
            The file system directory Eve will use as its working directory to
            store database files and other things.
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>eve.schemas</td>
          <td>true</td>
          <td>
            The schema configuration settings.
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>eve.disable.anonymous</td>
          <td>true</td>
          <td>
            If present disables anonymous binds.
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>eve.operation.sync</td>
          <td>true</td>
          <td>
            If present when requesting an InitialContext this property forces
            all partitions to sync their buffers to disk if they cache writes.
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>eve.operation.shutdown</td>
          <td>true</td>
          <td>
            If present when requesting an InitialContext this property
            gracefully shutsdown the server.  It returns a useless DeadContext
            which throws exceptions when used.
          </td>
        </tr>



        <tr>
          <td>eve.net.disable.protocol</td>
          <td>true</td>
          <td>
            Used when starting up the server to disable the networking frontend
            that handles LDAP protocol requests.
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>eve.net.passthru</td>
          <td>true</td>
          <td>
            Used to pass an existing network frontend to the server rather
            than having the server create its own instance.
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>eve.net.ldap.port</td>
          <td>true</td>
          <td>
            The LDAP port to use for servicing LDAP protocol requests if not
            on the standard port: 389.
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>eve.net.ldaps.port</td>
          <td>true</td>
          <td>
            The LDAP port to use for servicing secure LDAP protocol requests if
            not on the standard secure LDAP port: 636.
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>eve.db.partitions</td>
          <td>true</td>
          <td>
            The list of database partition identifiers.
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>eve.db.partition.suffix.</td>
          <td>false when adding partitions</td>
          <td>
            A key base for listing the suffixes of database partitions.  The
            identifier for the partition is appended to this base to form the
            key for the suffix of that partition.
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>eve.db.partition.indices.</td>
          <td>true</td>
          <td>
            A key base for listing the indices for database partitions.  The
            identifier for the partition is appended to this base to form the
            key for the suffix of that partition.
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>eve.db.partition.attributes.</td>
          <td>false when adding partitions</td>
          <td>
            A key base for listing the attributes and values for the suffix
            entries of partitions.  The identifier for the partition is
            appended to this base, then the name of attribute is appended to
            form the key for the attribuet in the suffix of that partition.
            More information on setting up partitions with this and other
            properties is <a href="/partitions.html">here</a>...
          </td>
        </tr>

      </table>
    </section>

    <section name="Embedding Eve">
      <p>
        Embedding Eve is really easy.  Just set the JNDI initial context
        factory and other security settings along with Eve specific properties
        to fire her up.  Here's a simple example of code that embeds Eve using
        the minimum configuration information:
      </p>

<source>
Hashtable env = new Hashtable();
env.setProperty( Context.PROVIDER_URL, "ou=system" );
env.setProperty( Context.INITIAL_CONTEXT_FACTORY, "org.apache.eve.jndi.EveContextFactory" );
InitialDirContext ctx = new InitialDirContext( env );
</source>

      <p>
        This code snippet starts up Eve on port 389 or the next available port.
        There is only one partition in the system hanging off of the "ou=system"
        naming context.  The server allows for anonymous binds and has two users
        preconfigured: a regular test user, <b>uid=akarasulu,ou=users,ou=system
        </b> with password <i>test</i>, and the super user <b>uid=admin,ou=system
        </b>, with password <i>secret</i>.
      </p>

      <p>
        <b>WARNING:</b> REMOVE THE TEST USER AND RESET THE PASSWORD ON THE ADMIN
        USER ACCOUNT AFTER STARTING EVE.
      </p>

      <p>
        Here's another more invovled configuration:
      </p>

<source>
Hashtable env = new Hashtable();

// Standard JNDI properties
env.setProperty( Context.PROVIDER_URL, "ou=system" );
env.setProperty( Context.INITIAL_CONTEXT_FACTORY, "org.apache.eve.jndi.EveContextFactory" );
env.setProperty( Context.SECURITY_PRINCIPAL, "uid=admin,ou=system" );
env.setProperty( Context.SECURITY_CREDENTIALS, "secret" );
env.setProperty( Context.SECURITY_PRINCIPAL, "uid=admin,ou=system" );

// Eve specifice JNDI properties
env.setProperty( EnvKeys.WKDIR, "/var/ldap" );
env.setProperty( EnvKeys.DISABLE_ANONYMOUS, "true" );
env.setProperty( EnvKeys.LDAP_PORT, "10389" );
env.setProperty( EnvKeys.PARTITIONS, "apache" );

// Setup new partition for Apache
BasicAttributes attrs = new BasicAttributes( true );
BasicAttribute attr = new BasicAttribute( "objectClass" );
attr.add( "top" );
attr.add( "domain" );
attr.add( "extensibleObject" );
attrs.put( attr );
attr = new BasicAttribute( "dc" );
attr.add( "apache" );
attrs.put( attr );
env.put( EnvKeys.SUFFIX + "apache", "dc=apache,dc=org" );     // suffix
env.put( EnvKeys.INDICES + "apache", "ou uid objectClass" );  // user indices
env.put( EnvKeys.ATTRIBUTES + "apache", attrs );              // suffix entry

// Fire it up!
InitialDirContext ctx = new InitialDirContext( env );
</source>

      <p>
        This configuration starts up the server on port 10389 with anonymous
        binds disabled.  Eve stores its database files under /var/ldap
        and creates a new application partition for Apache entries off of the
        <b>dc=apache,dc=org</b> naming context in addition to the system
        partition.  If you look closely at /var/ldap you'll see a directory
        names apache where you'll find even more database files.  This is a
        separate database partition for apache entries.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
