<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="akarasulu@apache.org">Alex Karasulu</author>
    <title>Partitions</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>
    <section name="Partitions">
      <p>
        Partitions are entry stores assigned to a naming context.  The idea
        behind a partition is that it stores a subset of the Directory
        Information Base (DIB).  Partitions can be implemented in any way so
        long as they adhere to interfaces.
      </p>

      <subsection name="Status">
        <p>
          Presently Eve has a single partition implementation which is used for
          both the system partition and user partitions.  It uses
          <a href="http://jdbm.sourceforge.net/">JDBM</a> as the underlying
          B+Tree implementation for storing entries.
        </p>

        <p>
          Other implementations are possible.  I'm particularly interested in
          memory based partitions either BTree based or based on something like
          Prevayer.
        </p>

        <p>
          Partitions have simple interfaces that can be used to align any data
          source to the LDAP data model thereby accessing it via JNDI or via
          LDAP over the wire.  This makes Eve very flexible as a bridge to
          standardize access to disparate data sources and formats.  Dynamic
          mapping based backends are also interesting.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="System Partition">
        <p>
          The system partition is a very special partition that is hardcoded to
          hang off of the <b>ou=system</b> naming context.  It is always present
          and contains administrative and operational information needed by the
          server to operate.  Hence its name.
        </p>

        <p>
          Eve's subsystems will use this partition to store information critical
          to their operation.  Things like triggers, stored procedures, access
          control instructions and schema information can be maintained here.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Root Nexus">
        <p>
          Several partitions can be assigned to different naming contexts within
          Eve so long as their names do not overlap such that one partition's
          naming context is contained within anothers.  The root nexus is a fake
          partition that does not really store entries.  It maps other entry
          storing partitions to naming contexts and routes backing store calls
          to the partition containing the entry associated with the operation.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="User Partitions">
        <p>
          User partitions are partitions added by users.  When you download and
          start using Eve you may want to create a separate partition to store
          the entries of your application.  To us user (sometimes also referred
          to as application) partitions are those that are not the system
          partition!  In the following section we describe how a user partition
          can be created in Eve.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Adding User Partitions">
      <p>
        Adding new application partitions to the server is a matter of
        setting the right JNDI environment properties.  These properties are
        used in both standalone and in embedded configurations.  We will show
        you how to configure partitions by example using properties files and
        programatically.
      </p>

      <subsection name="Using Properties Files">
        <p>
          Obviously properties files are not the best way to configure a large
          system like an LDAP server.  However properties files are the JNDI
          standard for pulling in configuration.  Eve as a JNDI provider tries
          to honor this.  Hence the use of a properties file for configuration.
          Below we have the configuration of two user defined partitions within
          a properties file.  These partitions are for the naming contexts:
          <code>dc=apache,dc=org</code> and <code>ou=test</code>.
        </p>

    <source>
# all multivalued properties are space separated like the list of partions here
eve.db.partitions=apache test

# apache partition configuration
eve.db.partition.suffix.apache=dc=apache,dc=org
eve.db.partition.indices.apache=ou cn objectClass uid
eve.db.partition.attributes.apache.dc=apache
eve.db.partition.attributes.apache.objectClass=top domain extensibleObject

# test partition configuration
eve.db.partition.suffix.test=ou=test
eve.db.partition.indices.test=ou objectClass
eve.db.partition.attributes.test.ou=test
eve.db.partition.attributes.test.objectClass=top organizationalUnit extensibleObject
    </source>

        <p>
          Although somewhat ugly the way we use properties for settings does
          work.  Hopefully we can build a tool on top of this to save the
          user some hassle.  Another approach may be to use XML or something
          easier to generate these properties from them.  For now its the best
          non-specific means we have to inject settings through JNDI environment
          Hashtables while still being able to load settings via properties
          files.  Properties from proerties files are the common denominator
          though.  Another means is however possible programatically.
        </p>
        <br></br>
        <h4>Partition Id</h4>
        <p>
          Breifly we'll explain these properties and the scheme used.  A
          partition's property set is associated as a set using the partition's
          id.  All partition ids are listed as a space separated list using the
          <b>eve.db.partitions</b> property: above it lists the ids for the two
          partitions, <i>apache</i> and <i>test</i>.
        </p>
        <br></br>
        <h4>Naming Context</h4>
        <p>
          Partitions need to know the naming context they will store entries
          for.  This naming context is also referred to as the suffix since all
          entries in the partition have this common suffix.  The suffix is a
          distinguished name.  The property key for the suffix of a partition is
          composed of the following property key base
          <b>eve.db.partition.suffix.</b> concatenated with the id of the
          partition: <b>eve.db.partition.suffix.</b><i>${id}</i>.  For example
          if the partition id is foo, then the suffix key would be,
          <b>eve.db.partition.suffix.foo</b>.
        </p>
        <br></br>
        <h4>User Defined Indices</h4>
        <p>
          Partitions can have indices on attributes.  Unlike OpenLDAP where you
          can build specific types of indices, Eve indices are of a single type.
          For each partition a key is assembled from the partition id and the
          property key base: <b>eve.db.partition.indices.</b><i>${id}</i>.  So
          again for foo the key for attribute indices would be
          <b>eve.db.partition.indices.foo</b>.  This value is a space separated
          list of attributeType names to index.  For example the apache
          partition has indices built on top of <b>ou</b>, <b>objectClass</b>
          and <b>uid</b>.
        </p>
        <br></br>
        <h4>Suffix Entry</h4>
        <p>
          When creating a context the root entry of the context corresponding
          to the suffix of the partition must be created.  This entry is
          composed of single-valued and multi-valued attributes.  We must
          specify these attributes as well as their values.  To do so we again
          use a key composed of a base, however this time we use both the id
          of the partition and the name of the attribute:
          <b>eve.db.partition.attributes.</b><i>${id}</i>.<i>${name}</i>.  So
          for partition foo and attribute bar the following key would be used:
          <b>eve.db.partition.attributes.foo.bar</b>.    The value of the key
          is a space separated list of values for the bar attribute.  For
          example the apache partition's suffix has an objectClass attribute
          and its values are set to: top domain extensibleObject.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Programaticly">
        <p>
          This is simple create a Hashtable and stuff it with those properties.
          But that's a real pain.  The other option is to set all the properties
          that way minus the one for the suffix entries attributes.  We have
          a shortcut where you can set an Attributes object within the Hashtable
          and it will get picked up instead of using the standard property
          scheme above.
        </p>

        <p>
          Simply put the Attributes into the Hashtable using the following
          key <b>eve.db.partition.attributes.</b><i>${id}</i>.  Below we show
          how this can be done for the same example above:
        </p>

<souce>
BasicAttributes attrs = new BasicAttributes( true );
BasicAttribute attr = new BasicAttribute( "objectClass" );
attr.add( "top" );
attr.add( "organizationalUnit" );
attr.add( "extensibleObject" );
attrs.put( attr );
attr = new BasicAttribute( "ou" );
attr.add( "testing" );
attrs.put( attr );

extras.put( EnvKeys.PARTITIONS, "testing example" );
extras.put( EnvKeys.SUFFIX + "testing", "ou=testing" );
extras.put( EnvKeys.INDICES + "testing", "ou objectClass" );
extras.put( EnvKeys.ATTRIBUTES + "testing", attrs );

attrs = new BasicAttributes( true );
attr = new BasicAttribute( "objectClass" );
attr.add( "top" );
attr.add( "domain" );
attr.add( "extensibleObject" );
attrs.put( attr );
attr = new BasicAttribute( "dc" );
attr.add( "example" );
attrs.put( attr );

extras.put( EnvKeys.SUFFIX + "example", "dc=example" );
extras.put( EnvKeys.INDICES + "example", "ou dc objectClass" );
extras.put( EnvKeys.ATTRIBUTES + "example", attrs );
</souce>

        <p>
          Ok that does not look any shorter.  We'll add to this in the future.
          Perhaps we enable the use of configuration beans that can be used
          with an SPI specific to Eve.  However this starts making your code
          Eve specific.  You can just change properties and use the SUN provider
          anymore to have your code be location independent.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Future Progress">
      <subsection name="Partition Nesting">
        <p>
          Today we have some limitations to the way we can partition the DIB.
          Namely we can't have a partition within a partition and sometimes this
          makes sense.  Eventually we intend to enable this kind of
          functionality using a special type of nexus which is both a router
          and a backing store for entries.  It's smart enough to know what to
          route verses when to use its own database.  Here's a <a href=
          "http://nagoya.apache.org/jira/browse/DIREVE-23">JIRA improvement</a>
          specifically aimed at achieving this goal.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Partition Variety">
        <p>
          Obviously we want as many different kinds of partitions as possible.
          Some really cool ideas have floated around out there for a while.
          Here's a list of theoretically possible partition types that might
          be useful or just cool:
        </p>

        <ul>
          <li>
            Partitions that use JDBC to store entries.  These would probably
            be way too slow.  However they might be useful if some mapping
            were to be used to represent an existing application's database
            schema as an LDAP DIT.  This would allow us to expose any database
            data via LDAP.
          </li>

          <li>
            Partitions using other LDAP servers to store their entries.  Why
            do this when introducing latency.  Perhaps you want to proxy other
            servers or make other servers behave like Eve.
          </li>

          <li>
            A partition that serves out the Windows registry via LDAP.  A
            standard mechanism to map the Windows registry to an LDAP DIT is
            pretty simple.  This would be a neat way to expose client machine
            registry management.
          </li>

          <li>
            A partition based on SleepyCat's JE.  I was going to try this
            and see how it performs against JDBM.
          </li>

          <li>
            A partition based on an in-memory BTree implementation.  This would
            be fast and really cool for storing things like schema info.  It
            would also be cool for staging data between memory and disk.
          </li>

          <li>
            A partition based on Prevalyer.  This is like an in-memory partition
            but you can save it at the end of the day.  This might be really
            useful especially for things the system partition which almost
            always need to be in memory.  The system partition can do this by
            using really large caches equal to the number of entries in the
            system partition.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Partitioning entries under a single context?">
        <p>
          Other aspirations include entry partitioning within a container
          context.  Imagine having 250 million entries under
          <code>ou=citizens,dc=census,dc=gov</code>.  You don't want all 250
          million in one partition but would like to sub partition these entries
          under the same context based on some attribute.  Basically we will be
          using the attribute's value to implement sub partitioning where within
          a single context we are partitioning entries.  The value is used to
          hash entries across buckets (the buckets are other partitions).  Yeah
          this is a bit wild but it would be useful in several situations.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
