<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="akarasulu@apache.org">Alex Karasulu</author>
    <title>LDAP Protocol Provider</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>
    <section name="Server's LDAP Protocol Provider">
      <subsection name="Provider API">
        <p>
          The network layer regardless of the implementation used (seda, sedang,
          or mina), defines protocol provider interfaces.  Protocol implementors
          only need to implement these interfaces to plug into these framework
          implementations.  A protocol provider essentially encapsulates the
          encoding/decoding of messages and request handlers (hooks) for the
          protocol.  The networking code handles the rest to make it all work.
        </p>

        <p>
          The directory server has one or more protocol provider
          implementations.  The primary implementation is for the LDAP protocol.
          The provider is rather simple in nature and has some unique properties
          which make it flexible enough to be used as an LDAP proxy server or
          an X.500 gateway server.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Design">
        <p>
          The server's LDAP protocol provider translates on the wire LDAP
          requests into JNDI LDAP operations.  Results from JNDI operations are
          then translated to LDAP responses pushed out on the wire.  This thin
          implementation makes the protocol layer efficient and easy to grasp.
        </p>

        <p>
          The protocol provider is independent of the JNDI provider used.  It is
          however dependent on the LDAP namespace.  Hence it can only work with
          LDAP JNDI providers like the SUN LDAP JNDI provider and the server's
          JNDI provider.
        </p>

        <p>
          The grunt of the work done by the protocol provider is within the
          request handlers.  There is a request handler for each LDAP request
          type.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
